Guide to the Gianfranco Sanguinetti Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Gianfranco Sanguinetti papers
1948-2013
GEN MSS 1181
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
20.45
(62 boxes)
The collection consists of correspondence, writings, notes, clippings, photocopies, posters, printed materials, legal papers, photographs, and digital media documenting the life and work of writer Gianfranco Sanguinetti. Correspondence with Guy Debord and others relates to Sanguinetti's involvement with the Situationist International, including its dissolution, as well as Sanguinetti's expulsion from France in 1971 and his writing under the pseudonym "Censor" in 1975. Writings include drafts of Sanguinetti's Prove dell'inesistenza di Censor, Rimedio a tutto, Del terrorismo e dello stato, and other works. Photographs, mostly by Sanguinetti, show fellow Situationists including Guy Debord, Mustapha Khayati, Raoul Vaneigem, and others.
Sanguinetti, Gianfranco, 1948-
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of correspondence, writings, notes, clippings, photocopies, posters, printed materials, legal papers, photographs, and digital media documenting the life and work of writer Gianfranco Sanguinetti. Correspondence with Guy Debord and others relates to Sanguinetti's involvement with the Situationist International, including its dissolution, as well as Sanguinetti's expulsion from France in 1971 and his writing under the pseudonym "Censor" in 1975. Writings include drafts of Sanguinetti's Prove dell'inesistenza di Censor, Rimedio a tutto, Del terrorismo e dello stato, and other works. Photographs, mostly by Sanguinetti, show fellow Situationists including Guy Debord, Mustapha Khayati, Raoul Vaneigem, and others.
Arrangement
Arranged in the order established by Gianfranco Sanguinetti and in which the collection was received from Christie's.
Sanguinetti organized the papers into fifty numbered binders. Papers have been removed from the binders, but remain organized and described in binder order.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Box 62 (digital media): Restricted fragile material. Access copies of digital files may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Christie's on the Edwin J. Beinecke Book Fund, 2013.
Gianfranco Sanguinetti
Gianfranco Sanguinetti (born 1948) is an Italian writer. He was a member of the Situationist International in the 1960s and, with Guy Debord, one of two final members when it dissolved in 1972.
Counterculture -- Europe; Born digital; Photographs; Situationist literature -- France -- Paris -- 20th Century; Situationist literature -- Italy -- 20th Century; Situationism -- France; Situationism -- Italy; Debord, Guy, 1931-1994; Khayati, Mustapha; Sanguinetti, Gianfranco, 1948-; Vaneigem, Raoul, 1934-; Internationale situationniste
- Binder 1, 1969 January-April (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents
  Preceding or preparatory documents of the Italian Section constitution. SI correspondence from January to April 1969. 95 files. MS - TS - Carbon MS/TS - 43 L MS (9 TS), from Debord including 10 unpublished + 1 telegram, 29 L GFS to Debord. Total: 43 L from Debord + 29 L to Debord. (About 65 pp. from Debord, including 10 unpublished).
- Binder 1, 1969 April-September (Box 2)
  Preceding or preparatory documents of the Italian Section constitution. SI correspondence from April to September 1969. 89 files. MS - TS - Carbon MS/TS - 43 L MS (9 TS), from Debord including 10 unpublished + 1 telegram, 29 L GFS to Debord. Total: 43 L from Debord + 29 L to Debord. (About 65 pp. from Debord, including 10 unpublished).
- Binder 2, 1969 October-December (Box 3)
  SI correspondence from October to December 1969. 85 files + 17 files on the bombs of 1969. MS - TS - Carbon MS/TS - (14 MS + 1 TS + 1 photocopy + 1 unpublished (photocopy) from Debord - Total 17 L from Debord + 21 L GFS to Debord). (About 47 pp. from Debord, including 2 unpublished).
- Binder 3, 1970 January-October (Box 4)
  SI Correspondence from January to October 1970. (Crisis and dissolution of the Italian Section.) 100 files. (9 L MS + 7 TS + 4 photocopies from Debord, 1 MS + 2 TS unpublished, Total: 23 L from Debord + 18 L GFS to Debord). (About 36 pp. from Debord, including 5 unpublished).
- Binder 3, 1970 October-December (Box 5)
  SI Correspondence from October to December 1970. (Crisis and dissolution of the Italian Section.) 19 files + 1 file of the media. (9 L MS + 7 TS + 4 photocopies from Debord, 1 MS + 2 TS unpublished, Total: 23 L from Debord + 18 L GFS to Debord). (About 36 pp. from Debord, including 5 unpublished).
- Binder 4, 1971 January-September (Box 6)
  SI Correspondence from January to September 1971. 100 files. (21 L MS + 8 TS + 1 photocopy from Debord + 11 unpublished, including 7 MS, 3 TS, 1 drawing of a game - Total: 41 L from Debord + 36 L GFS to Debord). (About 93 pp. from Debord, including 19 unpublished).
- Binder 4, 1971 September-December (Box 7)
  SI Correspondence from September to December 1971. 70 files. (21 L MS + 8 TS + 1 photocopy from Debord + 11 unpublished, including 7 MS, 3 TS, 1 drawing of a game - Total: 41 L from Debord + 36 L GFS to Debord). (About 93 pp. from Debord, including 19 unpublished).
- Binder 5, 1972 January-August (Box 8)
  Correspondence Guy - Alice from January to August 1972. Dissolution of the SI. 90 files. (26 MS + 10 TS + 2 telegrams + 1 Typographic document + 2 TS and 3 telegrams unpublished - Total 44 L from Debord + 36 L GFS to Debord. (+3 pp. from Debord printed in Italian: "Sull'Architettura selvaggia.") - (About 88 pp. from Debord, including 5 unpublished).
- Binder 5, 1972 August-December (Box 9)
  Correspondence with Guy and Alice from August to December 1972. Dissolution of the SI. 30 files. (26 MS + 10 TS + 2 telegrams + 1 Typographic document + 2 TS and 3 telegrams, unpublished - Total 44 L from Debord + 36 L GFS to Debord. (+3 pp. from Debord printed in Italian: "Sull'Architettura selvaggia.") - (About 88 pp. from Debord, including 5 unpublished).
- Binder 6, 1973 (Box 10)
  Correspondence with Guy, 1973. 35 files + 1 file of the media. (15 L MS + 3 TS + 2 unpublished MS from Debord - Total: 20 L from Debord + 6 L GFS to Debord). (About 37 pp. from Debord, including 4 unpublished).
- Binder 7, 1974 (Box 11)
  Correspondence Guy - Eduardo, etc., 1974. (The letters which are missing here are in 7BIS, "Censor Scandal.") 81 files. (29 L MS - including 5 MS + 1 telegram, unpublished - and TS from Debord, 11 L GFS to Debord). (About 40 pp. from Debord, including 8 unpublished).
- Binder 7BIS, 1974-1976 (Box 12)
  Correspondence Guy, 1974-1976. CENSOR Scandal. Here, the originals of my letters to Debord are also gathered from his archives, retrieved by Alice Debord in 2004. 120 files. (28 L MS and TS - including 7 MS and 3 photocopies, unpublished - from Debord, 43 L GFS to Debord). (About 55 pp. from Debord, including 13 unpublished).
- Binder 8, 1977-1979 (Box 13)
  About 100 pages of letters, pamphlets, newspapers, and manifestos. Correspondence with Guy, 1977-1979 on "Du Terrorisme" and on the revolts at Rome and Bologne. Moro Affair. The edition has 39 copies of "Tenzone di Anonimo Trovatore del Secolo XIII." 78 files. (14 L MS and TS from Debord - including 1 unpublished MS - 19 to Debord). (About 23 pp. from Debord, including 1 unpublished).
- Binder 8BIS, 1980-1984 (Box 14)
  Controversies surrounding the book "Du Terrorisme et de l'Etat," 1980-1984. Correspondences: 3 Typescripts of Debord (under the signatures of Lebovici, Els van Daele), J.F. Martos, Michel Prigent, Jaap Kloostermann, Van Daele, Mikis Anastassiadis, Carlos Ojeda, Roujau and Labrugere, Lebovici. Two texts of Sanguinetti from 2012 are added regarding these controversies: (1) the letter of Sanguinetti to Mustapha Khayati, 12/10/2012, and (2) "Souvenir," from Sanguinetti on the Doge. 116 files. (Note: Previously vol. 34)
- Binder 9, 1969-1972 (Box 15)
  Including 67 American Section records and 47 Scandinavian Section records + Manifestos and pamphlets. (Note: This is from the whole correspondence exchanged between the sections, as well as personal letters between members of the sections.) 121 files. (1 MS, 3 TS, 4 photocopies, from Debord, 4 GFS). (1 p MS, 9 TS, 1 PH from Debord).
- Binder 10, 1968-1972 (Box 16)
  Organizational questions - Strategic Debate. 77 files. (9 TS adn 13 photocopies from Debord + 1 translation, 24 GFS). (About 15 pp. TS, 28 pp. PH, 5 pp. Translation from Debord).
- Binder 11, 1971-1972 (Box 17)
  Expulsion from France - Vaconsin Affair - Trap of the Police - Ministry of Internal Affairs - Termination of M. Vaconsin at the Batonnier - Paris and Bentley apartment questions. 62 files. (1 telegram + 4 MS from Debord, including 2 MS + 1 TS unpublished, 1 L to Debord from GFS). (1 telegram, 3 pp. MS, 1 PH from Debord).
- Binder 12, 1968-1970 (Box 18)
  SI correspondence outside the Italian Section (1968-1970). 122 files.
- Binder 13, 1971- May 1972 (Box 19)
  SI Correspondence outside the Italian Section, in Italian, French, English (1971- May 1972). 115 files.
- Binder 13, May 1972-1987 (Box 20)
  SI Correspondence outside the Italian Section, in Italian, French, English (May 1972-December 1972) plus some later letters. 45 files.
  - Audio CD, 1 (Box 62)
    Conditions Governing Access
    Restricted fragile material. Access copies of digital files may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
- Binder 14, 1968-1976 (Box 21)
  Notebooks and translations MS + 3 chapters of "Traité" by Vaneigem, mimeographed + Letter editor Vallecchi, Italian translation of "La Société du Spectacle" TS orig. of Salvadori with corrections. 8 notebooks + 6 files.
- Binder 15, 1974-1976 (Box 22)
  Censor Scandal - 1 Record with 1 of the 520 copies (#149) of the original edition, numbered in monotype, of "Rapporto Veridico" with Sanguinetti's notes on the diversions and references in the book. Unpublished letter to Debord (1/7/74) in which Sanguinetti wrote the first draft of the Censor operation - One 3 pp. unpublished MS Record written by Sanguinetti and Debord with notes taken during a conversation on Censor - 7 Records with the original manuscript of the first version of the pamphlet - 1 Record with the intervention strategy and the diagram in the different phases of the scandal by Debord, unpublished. Index MS of the titles of the modified chapters by Debord - 1 Record with six pages TS of Debord to insert in the first chapter - 1 unpublished MS letter of Debord (2 pp.) with notes for the last chapter. 2 pp. unpublished TS of Debord with 3 propositions of corrections for page 3 of the preface - 2 pp. TS de Debord: "Proposition for a development apart - perhaps for the end of the pamphlet." - 7 pp. on 8 TS (with autograph corrections) of Debord to integrate in chapters I and VII - 2 pp. unpublished TS of Debord with notes to respond to journalistic follies + 2 articles of newspapers. - 3 unpublished Bristol MS tickets of Debord with citations and notes - 9 pp. printed by Mardersteig in monotype in order to serve as an example to the printer - 8 Records of 15 letters of thanks by the Italian ministry to the editor (Aldo Moro, Giulio Andreotti, Guido Carli, Bruno Visentini, Giorgio Amendola, Pietro Nenni, etc.). Agreement with Scotti Camuzzi, 1 Record with 4 pages of translation in English (Katharine Scott) of the "Préface." - 2 pp. of the book with MS notes of Sanguinetti. 2 pp. with unpublished text of Debord for Champ Libre in order to present the French edition. 49 files. (1 p. MS + 11 pp. published TS + 8 MS + 8 unpublished TS of Debord).
- Binder 15BIS, 1975-1976 (Box 23)
  Complete original manuscript of "Prove dell'Inesistenza di Censor" - Prepatory notes, with 1 p., 4 Bristol MS tickets and two drawings of Europe and Italy of Debord (unpublished). Plus some letters, my deposition MS to the trial of Catanzaro. - Record of press with the news of the arrest of General Maletti and Captain La Bruin of the Secret Services after my deposition to the judge of Catanzaro. - Copy of my suppression at the France-Switzerland border (2/11/1976) + copy of "Le Monde" (2/24/1976) with the famous "Déclaration des Éditions Champ Libre," written by Debord some days after my arrest and supression at the border and published on half a page of "Monde" (on p. 7). 34 files.
- Binder 16, 1975-1976 (Box 24)
  Press on the Censor Scandal (1975-1976). 99 files.
- Binder 17, 1969 (Box 25)
  About 300 pp. of MS and TS articles for the first of the "Internazionale Situazionista" review, (1969) + corrected printing proofs, diverted advertisements, illustrations. 24 files.
- Binder 18, 1968-1980 (Box 26)
  Bringing together the Situationist or pro-Situationist leaflets and small editions between 1968 and 1980 in several languages, including drafts of manifestos.
- Binder 19, 1968-1982 (Box 27)
  Collection of TS documents and prints related to the different movements between 1968 and 1982 in Italian and French. 33 files.
- Binder 20, 1968-1974 (Box 28)
  Posters and leaflets printed in several languages (French, Italian, Arabic, Spanish, English, Polish, Swedish, Greek) 1968-1974. 79 files.
- Binder 21, 1977 (Box 29)
  Complete unpublished manuscript of "Rimedio a Tutto" (of GFS - 1977). XV Chapters. About 600 pp. 28 files.
- Binder 22, 1977 (Box 30)
  Original corrected TS of "Rimedio a Tutto" (except chapters III and X: Chapter X, together with the "Préface," the "Avertissement de l'Auteur" and "Dédicace aux mauvais ouvriers," was published in the book: "Del Terrorismo e dello Stato, 1979). 15 files.
- Binder 23, 1977 (Box 31)
  Carbon copies of the TS of "Rimedio a Tutto, " including chapter X but not chapters III, VIII, IX, XII. 14 files.
- Binder 24, 1979 (Box 32)
  Sanguinetti, "Del Terrorismo e dello Stato," carbon copy: 1) Index, 2) Warning, 3) Foreward (1 p. missing), 4) text, 5) Preface to the French Edition (70 pp.) + 6) Excerpts of english translation (15 pp.) + the same text, photocopies with notes of the anarchist Joe Fallisi (39 pp.). (Total = 124 pp.). 7 files.
- Binder 24BIS, 1979 (Box 33)
  MS and TS, Sanguinetti, "Del Terrorismo e dello Stato" (Original manuscript, MS draft + Preface to the French edition). About 200 pp. 17 files.
- Binder 25, 1979 (Box 34)
  Sanguinetti, "Del Terrorismo e dello Stato," corrected proofs (about 180 pp.). 5 files.
- Binder 26, 1979 (Box 35)
  Translation: "Du Terrorism et de l'Etat" - Typescript copy. French translation of JF Martos + Spanish translation of Carlos Ojeda TS + MS (About 300 pp. + including 125pp MS.). 5 files.
- Binder 27, 1971-1998 (Box 36)
  Manifestos, leaflets and printed documents of the 1970s (in Italian and French). (Note: We put in this volume the binder formerly entitled 27 BIS.) 73 files.
- Binder 28, 1967-1987 (Box 37)
  (Italian, English, French) Small, rare editions, years '70/'80. 39 files.
- Binder 29, 1972 (Box 38)
  Original carbon typescript with MS corrections of Debord of "La Véritable Scission dans l'Internationale." (It is missing p. 37). + 1 p. MS of Debord's notes. 2 files.
- Binder 30, 1972 (Box 39)
  Original corrected unpublished Italian translation typscript of "La Vera Scissione nell'Internazionale. 100 pp. 2 files.
- Binder 31, 1975-1976 (Box 40)
  Film project on Censor (written by Sanguinetti with the collaboration of Debord). Two editions of Censor + Photocopies of the script of the film "La Société du Spectacle with notes and diversions of Debord. 12 files.
- Binder 32, 1979-1980 (Box 41)
  MS original of Sanguinetti's unpublished pamphlet against the anti-terrorism Prosecutor Pier Luigi Vigna after the killing of Aldo Moro: "Del Modo tenuto da Pier Luigi Vigna, magistrato fiorentino nel frabbricare l'accusa di Terrorismo contro Sanguinetti e altri," 1979. About 60 pp. 7 files.
- Binder 33, 1977 (Box 42)
  Revolts and movements of 1977 at Rome and Bologna. 1 MS of Sanguinetti's notes. Unedited book project. Correspondences. Manifestos. Leaflets. Original unpublished photos. Media files. 25 files.
- Binder 33, 1977 (Box 43)
  Revolts and movements of 1977 at Rome and Bologna. 1 MS of Sanguinetti's notes. Unedited book project. Correspondences. Manifestos. Leaflets. Original unpublished photos. Media files. 1 oversized file.
- Binder 34, 1971-2007 (Box 44)
  International press on Sanguinetti starting from 1971. 62 files.
- Binder 35, 1948-1983 (Box 45)
  Police, Judiciary, Military documents (1960-1983). 1 telegram from Debord (published) and 2 unpublished photocopies (including the originals in Binder 11). 69 files.
- Binder 36, 1971-1999 (Box 46)
  Unpublished correspondence, original MS and TS, with the bankers Raffaele Mattioli, Enrico Cuccia, and others, and with the lawyer Ariberto Magnoli (1971-1999). Plus documentation. 110 files.
- Binder 37, 1981-1986 (Box 47)
  MS and TS unpublished correspondence of GFS with the revolutionary Riccardo d'Este, in prison for armed struggle, between 1981 and 1986. Unpublished. 61 files.
- Binder 38, 1970-2004 (Box 48)
  Correspondence with Alice Becker (1995-2004) and correspondance photocopies with Debord in view of the poblication. About 500 pp. + original correspondence with Alice Becker. 26 files.
- Binder 39, 1966-2013 (Box 49)
  More than 150 original unpublished photographs, much of which are single-copy, taken mostly by GFS (except where GFS is present), with the Situationists and their friends starting from 1969. In these photos one finds Guy Debord, Alice Becker, Mustapha Khayati, Hakima Berrada, René Viénet, Raoul Vaneigem, Fatimah, J. V. Martin, Gianfranco Sanguinetti, Connie Occhialini, Celeste, Christian Sébastiani, Paolo Salvadori, Claudio Pavan, Maria Cristina Michiara, René Riesel, John Horelick, Jane, Tony Verlaan, Robert Chasse, Bruce Ellwell, Eduardo Rothe, Techi, Alain Chevalier, François de Beaulieu, Patrick Cheval, Angéline Neveu, Mario Masanzanica, Rocco Muzio, Teresa Mattei, Françoise Sullivan, Gerhard Weiss, Magdalena Michels and others. They were taken at Milan, Venice, Bologna, Florence, Siena, Monteriggioni, S. Gimignano, Greve in Chianti, S. Andrea in Percussina, etc. On the back of the photos there are notes with the names. At the end of the file are about thirty photos of documentation of the archival work and of subsequent photos. (Attached to this binder is a disk on which more than 250 photos were scanned- some of which are in double.) 41 files.
  - CD-R of scanned photographs, 1 (Box 62)
- Binder 40, 1968-2000 (Box 50)
  MS and TS. 1)"Internationale Situationniste" #13, unpublished. 10 files with articles (1970/71) (66 pp.). "Avertissement," unpublished of Debord (14 pp.) original carbon TS with corrections. 2) Unpublished notes and manuscripts of GFS (1968-1973). 3) Eduardo Rothe. 2 files. 1 notebook with unpublished handwritten MS book, illustrated with original drawings: "La Coherencia Armada - Manual de Tecnicas Insurrecionales." 100 pp. + 1 album of subversive comics, unpublished, illustrated of original drawings (of Rothe) A4 format, full page colored. 4) Raoul Vaneigem, TS photocopy: "Toast aux Ouvriers révolutionnaires" - October 1972. 5) GFS - "Le Lotte di Classe in Italia 1969-1972." Unpublished MS and TS (about 120 pp.). 6) GFS - "Gli Operai d'Italia e la Rivolta di Reggio Calabria." Original MS (22 pp.), TS + prints of proofs. 7) Mustapha Khayati - "Della Miseria nell'ambiente studentesco" (proof sheets for the edition of the "Estremismo coerente dei Situazionisti"). 8) GFS - unpublished MS pamphlet (unfinished): "Soluzioni tecniche di Questioni sociali e politiche. Un Contributo alla Strategia e alla Tattica dei Servizi di Protezione dello Stato. Manuale pratico ad uso dello Stato Maggiore." (about 22 pp.) 9) Correspondence Michele Bernstein, Ralph Rumney. 49 files.
- Binder 40, 1979-1984 (Box 51)
  MS and TS. 10) Holland Affair - Attali - Bercoff - Censor plagiarism 1982-1989. 11) "Proletari non illudiamoci: Toni Negri e' innocente," 1979. Pamphlet project. 14 files.
- Binder 41, 1984 (Box 52)
  Murder of Gérard Lebovici, media files + letter of Jacques Philipponneau + pamphlet "Les mots et les Balles." 25 files.
- Binder 42, 1969-1998 (Box 53)
  American media. 11 files.
- Binder 43, 1977-1981 (Box 54)
  Pseudo-Berlinguer Scandal - Unpublished GFS preface to "Lettere agli Eretici." Pamphlet against Giulio Bollati di Saint-Pierre. Correspondence with P.F. Ghisleni. 60 files.
- Binder 44, 1972-2013 (Box 55)
  Media on the Situationists. 35 files.
- Binder 45, 1968-2004 (Box 56)
  Publishers and typographers, correspondences. 88 files.
- Binder 46, 1964-1967 (Box 57)
  Sanguinetti - manuscripts and typescripts 1964-1967 - unpublished. 17 files.
- Binder 47, 1968-2008 (Box 58)
  Sanguinetti - manuscripts and typescripts - unpublished GFS. 45 files.
- Binder 48, 1961-1999 (Box 59)
  Addendum I. This folder is not ordered. 24 files.
- Binder 49, 1968-2013 (Box 60)
  Addendum II. This binder is not ordered. 13 files.
- Binder 50, 1989-2001 (Box 61)
  Addendum III.
- Hard drive containing scans of the collection, circa 2013; 1 (Box 62)